ALANI JIMMY

CURRICULUM VITAE

MINISTRY OF LANDS HOUSING AND URBAN DEVELOPMENT P.O BOX 7096, KAMPALA

+256 772449748.

alanijim@gmail.comm
Skype ID: alanijim1

CORE SKILLS AND COMPETENCIES:

Over the period of 11 years as a computer scientist and a GIS Professional, I have acquired technical skills and hands on experience in the areas of Geographical Information Systems Development, system administration, software development, Information System Management, Server Management, programming, networking, internet banking, and troubleshooting related problems. I acquired this wealth of knowledge during my tenure as the Information Communication and Technology (ICT) Officer with Ministry of Lands, Information Technology /Banking Assistant at Crane Bank Uganda Limited and a volunteer with the International Rescue Committee (IRC), Kampala. I am currently a team leader with Ministry of Lands, and I have great leadership and communication skills. I have provided strategic direction to the team at Ministry of Lands-on-lands information management including software development, roll out and implementation. I am results- oriented, hardworking and a team player with high integrity. I also provided technical oversight and support to regional offices including monitoring and evaluating the functionality of the services installed.

Technical Competences:

- Database management
- Geographical Information System Development
- Networking
- Capacity building, mentoring, and coaching of staff and users on lands information systems and other technical areas.
- Development of information/ database management systems
- Providing financial/budgetary support to the Ministry of Lands
- Design, oversight, and implementation of lands information systems software

WORK EXPERIENCE:

Ag Principal ICT / GIS Officer (Deputy In charge NLIC), Uganda National Land Information Centre (NLIC): March 2023 to Date

As Ag Principal ICT Officer with NLIC my roles and responsibilities include taking on management responsibilities of the Uganda National land Information Centre as deputy In charge. Key tasks include but not limited to:

- Geospatial Data analysis for Ministry of Lands, Housing and Urban development
- Technical Support Coordinator for Land Valuation Management Information System Project, sponsored by World Bank Under the Competitiveness Enterprise Development Project. (CEDP)
- Technical Support Coordinator for Systematic Land Adjudication and Certification Data Capture and Processing Tool.
- Providing support to the Ministry of Lands on the budgetary, performance and efficiency of the hardware suitable for use and in line with organisational requirements and policies,

As Senior ICT Officer with NLIC my roles and responsibilities included Heading the Software Development Section at the center. Key tasks include but not limited to:

- Participating in the development of Terms of Reference for the Enhancement of the National land Information system Enhancement project.
- Participating in the development of the Land Valuation Management Information system
- Developed the Terms of Reference for the Systematic Land Adjudication and Certification Data Capture and Processing Tool for Land Administration in Uganda.
- Providing technical oversight and leading the software development section at the National Land Information Centre in Uganda,
- Providing support to the Ministry of Lands on the budgetary, performance and efficiency of the hardware suitable for use and in line with organisational requirements and policies,

ICT Officer, Uganda National Land Information Centre (NLIC): April 2016 to May 2022

As ICT Officer with NLIC my roles and responsibilities included providing oversight in software development, maintenance and roll out in the country. Key tasks include but not limited to:

- Coordinating the development team of the DeSINLISI Project and MLHUD Development team
- Providing technical oversight and leading the software development section at the National Land Information Centre in Uganda,
- Configuring and customization of the Uganda Land Information System
- Fixing
- Providing support to the Ministry of Lands on the budgetary, performance and efficiency of the hardware suitable for use and in line with organisational requirements and policies,
- Monitoring and evaluation of the performance of the Uganda national land information system database in the head office as well as zonal offices,
- Centrally creating and managing users on all the zonal offices across the country
- Manage Land Information System database and data
- Perform data restoration and recovery
- Train users on the land information system
- Manage the Uganda Land Information System Data Integrity
- Organise Ministry open days for the public to carry out searches on the Uganda Land Information system
- Provide comprehensive, quality and timely reports
- Ensure adequate data collection and analysis to inform senior management on the functionality of the NLIS
- Perform regular data backup.

<u>Information Computer Technology (ICT) Officer In Charge, Masaka Ministry of Lands Zonal Office: January 2016</u> to March 2016

Key tasks accomplished as ICT Officer In Charge:

- Conducted regular site server management and ensured its functionality and efficiency as well siting its location in a good and secure environment
- Created users both on the computer domains and registry workstation and regularly updated the information as per need
- I also created and provided user rights in compliance with individual roles and responsibilities in line with the Land Information System requirement
- Conducted weekly data backups to ensure data/ Information safety and integrity
- Trained users on the Land Information System and provided regular mentoring and coaching to ensure quality of work

- Conducted regular repairs and maintenance of the hardware and software in the zonal office
- Consolidated timely monthly reports for the ICT Department, including systems performance in general
- Managed the Local Area Network (LAN) for users

ICT Officer In Charge, Mbarara Ministry of Lands Zonal Office: August 2013 to December 2015

As ICT Officer In Charge of Mbarara Ministry of Lands zonal office, my roles and responsibilities and accomplishments included:

- Ensuring timely and regular server management at the site for maximum functionality as well siting its location in a good and secure environment
- Created users both on the computer domains and registry workstation
- Issued user rights in line with individual duties in accordance with the Land Information System management protocols and policy
- Carried out weekly data backups to ensure safety of data/ Information
- Trained users on the Land Information System
- Ensured regular repairs and maintenances of the hardware and software in the zonal office
- Consolidated timely monthly reports for the ICT Department, and the Systems performance in general

Information Technology/Bank Assistant, Crane Bank Uganda Limited: March 2013 to August 2013

As IT/Bank Assistant my roles and responsibilities included but not limited to:

- Monitoring ATMs to ensure all were functional
- Timely client accounts opening and creating internet banking services
- Ensured all computers are on the network and managed the Local Area Network (LAN)
- Conducted regular hardware maintenance
- Installed software on the computers as required

MAJOR ACHIEVEMENTS

In the 7 years as an information and communication technology professional, I have registered to mention but a few of the achievements listed below:

- Deputy In Charge of the National Land Information Centre.
- Leading a team in the software Development section at Ministry of Lands that is responsible for the maintenance of the Uganda Land Information System UgNLIS
- Developed a fit for purpose GIS (Systematic Land Adjudication And certification Software) under funding by World Bank for the Ministry of Lands, Housing and Urban Development
- Developed an API (Application Programming Interface) for Ministry of Lands Housing and Urban Development for sharing land information with other Government Agencies, as requested by NITA-U
- Developed the Document management Information System for National Land Information centre
- Set up and managed the Geospatial Data Processing Centre at the Department for Surveys and Mappings.
- Deployed the current and latest version of the Uganda Land Information System UgNLIS, to all the 22 ministry zonal offices including Uganda Land Commission
- Duplicating MZO UgNLIS into testing environment with working UgNLIS software and data
- Supporting all the 22 zonal offices on the application and data related issues
- Customized the UgNLIS from the UgNLIS source code
- Customized business rules in the Uganda land Information system
- Fixed bugs and other related system issues in the Uganda land Information System
- Developed a document management System for Ministry of Lands Housing and Urban Development
- Documenting all procedures and solutions for the bugs fixed in the application
- Participated in the Migration of the Legacy System (data) to the UgNLIS

EDUCATION

Month and year	Qualification	Institution
2023 - 2024	Graduate Student of MS in Cartography and Geographical Information System Development	University of Wisconsin – Madison, USA
2022 JANUARY To 2022 DECEMBER	Capstone Certificate in Cartography and GIS Development	University of Wisconsin – Madison, USA
2008 to 2011	Bachelor's degree of Science in Computer Science (Second Class Upper)	Uganda Christian University, Mukono, Uganda.

CERTIFICATES ATTAINED AND TRAININGS UNDERTAKEN:

Relevant Training and Certificates Attained:

Year	Training/ Certificate awarded	Institution
2020	Certificate in Programming for Data Science with Python	Udacity
2015	Information Management Technology (ICT) Training	Makerere ICT Solutions
2014	Certificate in CCNA	Aptech Computer Education
2011	Certificate of merit in academic excellent performance	Uganda Christian University
2010	Certificate in Systems Administration	ICT Labs, Ntinda